1 Introduction

1.1 Background

The Standard Matchplay Rules (SMR) represent a significant shift in the way that the rules of table soccer, or foosball, are imagined and presented.

The project was born from a recognition that the 2016 ITSF rulebook was showing its age; from the original ruleset adopted by the ITSF, successive changes resulted in a document that was in need of a refresh.

To serve these ends a new scheme was created; the SMR introduced a novel terminology consistently applied in the description of the matchplay processes and proscriptive rules.

SMR Version 1.0 was the first deliverable in this project, a strict ‘translation’ of the 2016 rulebook that did not include any rules changes. Avoiding rule changes allowed errors and omissions to be more readily identified, so that corrections and clarifications resulting from feedback could then be applied and released as SMR Version 1.1. Neither of the Version 1 documents included any rules changes.

Now that the SMR has stabilised, rule changes can be introduced, and SMR Version 2.0 is the first document in the SMR series to include changes to the rules.

1.2 Philosophy

The bedrock of the Matchplay Rules is a set of definitions which are referenced throughout the document. The consistent use of a coherent set of definitions encapsulates complexity, which allows the rules to be both precise and brief. It also minimises ambiguity, subjectivity, redundancy and contradiction within the document.

The objective of the SMR approach is to facilitate:

● rule interpretation and refereeing

● accurate translation into other languages

● the creation of ITSF Matchplay rule books for other event types

● the introduction of a standard foosball terminology

1.3 Document Structure

Italicised words or phrases are defined terms, which are collected and ordered alphabetically in the

Definitions section.

The sections generally follow a common pattern, the first part of which typically describes what the players can or must do. The next part contains proscriptive rules, which state what a player must not do, and the penalty to be paid for infraction.

Rules and penalties are named, rather than numbered. The details of the process to follow for each

penalty are collected in a separate Penalties section.

Matchplay rules sometimes contain interpretations. While interpretations are not formal rules, they are useful for communicating how common or edge cases are handled.

1.4 Interpretation of Rules

If any ambiguity or conflict is found in the rules the following process should be used to attempt resolution:

1. The English language version of this document takes precedence over translations.

2. Assume the rules and definitions are complete and cover the case even by omission.

3. Refer to the interpretations.

4. Request an interpretation from the ITSF Rules Commission.

1.5 Scope

This document defines the ITSF Standard Matchplay rules of Table Soccer, or foosball, covering the matchplay rules for both standard singles and standard doubles events played on a single table. Matchplay rules for other event types are not described in this document.

The Standard Matchplay Rules define how matches are played; they do not cover all aspects of tournament conduct, substance use or the dress code.

4 The Prelude

A match begins with the prelude, a process which includes the following sequence of events:

● Perform the initial flip

● Choose the first kick-off or table side

● Each team adopts their table side

● Each team adopts their initial playing positions

● Agree on the ball supply

● Agree to begin play

The prelude begins with the initial flip, typically a coin toss between one player from each team. The winner of the initial flip has the option of either taking the first kick-off or picking the table side for the first game, with the loser of the initial flip taking the remaining option. Once the winning team makes their choice they cannot change their decision.

The team with the option to pick the table side must then do so, and each team must adopt their nominated side. In standard doubles the team with the first kick-off must adopt their respective playing positions before the other team; one player controls the goalkeeper rod and the 2-rod and the other player controls the 5-rod and the 3-rod.

During the prelude either team can practice in order to evaluate the condition of the table, check that the table is level, and to test the table sides and the balls.

The prelude is also an opportunity to perform routine maintenance and if necessary to request table maintenance; once active play has begun table maintenance can only be called for a sudden alteration to the table. Either team can request a referee during the prelude.

Players should initiate and complete the prelude in a timely manner. Time-outs are not allowed during the prelude. A referee has the authority to call conduct violations during the prelude.

When both teams agree that they are ready to play, the team which has the kick-off initiates the ready protocol. The prelude ends when the player with possession asks “Ready?” whereupon all matchplay rules are in force.

4.1 Ball Supply

During the prelude the players must agree on the set of balls that will be used during the match. If there is disagreement then new balls must be used. This set of balls constitutes the ball supply. Once the first opening sequence of the match has begun permission must be obtained to add a ball to or remove a ball from the ball supply.

The player with the kick-off has the choice of which ball is selected from the ball supply. Once the ready protocol has begun the ball can be exchanged with permission during the restart or a break.

Rule: Ball Exchange

A player must not exchange the ball in play with another from the ball supply without permission. Penalty: Referee discretion, possible Penalty Shot

Rule: Ball Supply Change

A player must not add a ball into or remove a ball from the ball supply without permission. Penalty: Referee discretion, possible Penalty Shot

Rule: Ball Replacement Request Declined

During active play, if a player makes a request to replace the ball then the referee shall determine if the ball is fit for play. If the ball is declared unfit for play it shall be replaced, otherwise it shall not be replaced and there shall be a penalty for the requesting team. Penalty: Charged Time-out

6 Possession

The concept of possession relates to which rod, and by extension which player and team, has ownership of the ball at any point in time. Possession is either active possession, paused possession or implicit possession.

Active possession on a rod begins when the ball is reachable by that rod during active play, and ends when the ball is no longer reachable. Active possession is time-limited; the duration of the possession is measured by a possession clock and limited by the rules.

Paused possession is when a player has possession of the ball on a rod during a pause or interrupt.

Implicit possession is when the ball is about to be given to a specific rod to be put into play following a dead ball, a ball off table, a goal scored or an infraction interrupt.

In a refereed match active possession time limits are enforced by the referee; players cannot declare possession time infractions. In an unrefereed match, a player who believes that a possession time limit is being breached may interrupt play in order to request a referee. The player with possession will then restart play with the match under referee time control.

If a spinning ball becomes unreachable anywhere behind the 2-rod, the possession clock is suspended until the ball becomes reachable or dead.

Rule: Time Limit on 3-rod

A single active possession on the 3-rod must not exceed 15 seconds. Penalty: Goalie rod Possession Award

Rule: Time Limit on 5-rod

A single active possession on the 5-rod must not exceed 10 seconds. Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Rule: Time Limit on Goalie Rods

A single active possession on the goalie rods must not exceed 15 seconds. Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

6.1 Relinquishing Possession of a Precarious Ball

A player with possession of a ball that is stopped and precariously close to the goal has the option to relinquish possession to the opposing team’s 5-rod prior to expiry of the goalie rod possession time.

The ball is considered to be precarious if it’s stopped and if any part of the ball is behind the goalkeeper rod and directly in front of the goalmouth, for example if it is:

● overhanging the goal line

● reachable behind the goalkeeper

● pinned to the lip of the goalmouth, a goalpost or the crossbar

A player who wishes to relinquish possession of a precarious ball must initiate a player interrupt and declare that they want to relinquish the ball. If the ball is precarious, consent to reach into the playing area is implicit and the ball is then retrieved and placed at the opposing team’s central 5-rod figure for a restart. If the player believes that a precarious ball is a dead ball, the onus is on them to demonstrate that the ball is unreachable before reaching into the playing area.

The ball must be stopped in order to be precarious, therefore if a player legally declares their intent to relinquish a precarious ball and the ball subsequently drops into the goal, then the goal will not count; the ball is retrieved and given to the opposing 5-rod.

If a player declares an intent to relinquish a moving ball then they have violated the Distracting Activity rule and the opposing team has the option to continue from the current location or to take possession on their 5-rod.

7 Breaks in Play

A break is a temporary suspension of active play, any of the following:

● pause

○ between points

○ between games

○ time-out

● dead ball

● ball off table

● interrupt

○ player interrupt

○ infraction interrupt

○ disruption

The pauses are: between points, between games, and time-out. All pauses are time-limited, i.e. they have a specified maximum duration.

An interrupt is an exceptional break in play which can occur at any time, i.e. during active play, during a break, or during the restart that follows a break.

Although some breaks are not time-limited, the ball should always be put back into play as soon as possible. If the referee announces “Play!”, the restart process begins and the player with possession must put the ball back into play without delay.

7.1 Pauses

A pause is a routine break in active play which is time-limited, meaning that it must not exceed a maximum duration specified as follows:

Table: Time management for pauses

Pause | Pause begins when | Maximum duration
Between points | Goal scored that does not end the game | 5 seconds
Between games | Goal scored that ends the game | 90 seconds
Time-out | Player calls a time-out | 30 seconds

The referee may use a timer to enforce the limits during a pause. Pauses can be terminated before the time limit expires by the verbal agreement of both teams. When the pause ends the ball must be put into play with a restart.

7.1.1 Point Scored

A goal is scored when the ball completely crosses the goal line. If the goal is legally scored then a point is awarded to the appropriate team, who must record it on the relevant tally markers.

The team that conceded the point then puts the ball into play with a kick-off.

If both teams agree that a point was not marked for a goal scored earlier in the same game, then the point shall be given. If the teams do not agree then no point shall be given.

Rule: Illegal Mark

A player must not mark up a point for a goal that was not legally scored. Penalty:

● First in match: Referee discretion, possible Penalty Shot

● Subsequent in match: Referee discretion, possible Penalty Shot. Head referee discretion,

possible forfeiture of game or match

Interpretation

1. If the ball completely crosses the goal line and then leaves the goal, it’s still a goal.

2. Inadvertent errors in score marking are not subject to penalty.

3. An own goal scored as a result of an infraction by the same team will effectively count,

because the opposing team has the option to continue play from the current position.

7.1.1.1 Between Points

The maximum duration of the pause between points is 5 seconds, a period which may be terminated early by agreement of the teams.

Between points both teams are allowed to:

● change playing positions (in standard doubles)

● call a time-out

7.1.1.2 Between Games

The maximum duration of the pause between games is 90 seconds, a period which may be terminated early by agreement of the teams.

Between games both teams are allowed to:

● practice

● call a time-out

● change table sides (where permitted)

● change playing positions (in standard doubles)

● change handles (where permitted)

A time-out taken between games counts towards the total in the following game.

After completion of the first game played, either team may request a change of table sides, in which case the teams must change sides. If the teams do change sides then they must subsequently change sides after every game in the match, but if they do not change sides after the first game played then the teams must stay on the same sides for the entire match.

Under some circumstances the tournament director may generally disallow changing table sides.

7.1.2 Time-out

A time-out is a pause during which the players may leave the table and converse with each other and with other people. The maximum duration of a time-out is 30 seconds.

Each team has two time-outs per game. The number of available time-outs decreases when a team legally calls a time-out or when the referee charges a team with a time-out. A time-out taken between games counts towards the total in the following game.

A team can call a time-out:

● during active play if they have active possession of the ball

● during any of the following breaks and the subsequent restart:

○ a pause, i.e.

■ between points

■ between games

■ time-out

○ dead ball

○ ball off table

Teams are not permitted to call time-outs during interrupts, nor during the restart which follows an interrupt to active play unless they have possession.

If the requesting team has active possession of a stopped ball then the time-out begins immediately. However, if the ball is moving then active play continues and the time-out begins only when the ball stops moving under possession of the same rod.

A team is deemed to have called a time-out if a player on that team releases both handles for more than three seconds, or releases both handles and turns away from the table.

The team requesting the time-out must mark it on the relevant tally marker if the table has them.

During a time-out any player may reach into the playing area in order to lubricate their rods or wipe the playfield. The ball may be handled only with permission, after which it must be replaced in the same position. Players are not allowed to practice during a time-out.

The time-out ends when the 30 second period has expired, or earlier by agreement of both teams. If a referee is present they will instruct the teams when play must restart; any delay is then subject to Delay of Game infraction. In standard doubles, players in either team may switch positions when returning to the table. After the time-out ends play is restarted by the player with possession.

Rule: Time-out Limit

A team must not call a time-out when they have none remaining in the game. Penalty:

● First in game:

○ During active play: 5-rod Possession Award ○ During a pause or restart: Warning

● Subsequent in game: Penalty Shot

Rule: Charged Time-out With None Remaining

A team must not be charged with a time-out when they have none remaining. Penalty: Penalty Shot

Rule: Illegal Time-out

A team must not call a time-out during active play if they do not have possession of the ball. A team must not perform a transfer or a transition immediately after requesting a time-out. Penalty: Distraction

Rule: Double Time-out

Once a team initiates the opening sequence following a time-out that they called during active play, they must not call another time-out before performing a transition. Penalty: Goalie rod Possession Award

Rule: Disallowed Time-out

A player must not call a time-out:

● during an interrupt

● during the restart following an interrupt to active play if their team does not have possession Penalty: Time-out disallowed

Rule: Premature Transition

When restarting play after a time-out taken during active play, once the player with possession assumes control of the rod of possession the ball must not be transitioned prior to the start of the ready protocol.

Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Interpretation

1. In standard doubles it is a distraction for a player to perform a transition at the same time as,

or immediately after their partner calls a time-out.

2. It is a distraction if a player requests a time-out and then loses possession before the ball

stops moving.

3. After calling a time-out, active play continues until the ball stops moving. Therefore before the

ball comes to rest a player is at risk of, for example, exceeding the possession time limit or scoring an own goal.

4. After the time-out begins, an inadvertent transfer or transition is not an infraction; the ball is

returned to its original location.

5. A player in possession of a stopped ball may release both handles for up to three seconds,

e.g. to wipe sweat away.

7.2 Dead Ball

A ball is dead if it is stationary and not reachable. A ball is declared dead by the referee, or in the absence of a referee, by agreement of the teams.

A dead ball is put back into play without delay with a restart from the specified location:

Location of dead ball | Where to restart
Between the 5-rods | Kick-off
Behind the 5-rod | Any figure on the nearest goalie rod

Rule: Playing the Ball Dead

A player must not intentionally play the ball dead. Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Rule: Flex Infraction

A player must not make contact with an otherwise unreachable ball by flexing a rod. Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Interpretation

1. A ball stuck in a serving hole or on top of the goalkeeper rod is a dead ball.

2. A player must not play the ball dead by moving the ball out of reach by upward movements of

the figure.

7.3 Ball off Table

The ball is declared off table by the referee, or in the absence of a referee, by agreement of the teams. The team responsible for the controlled transition which played the ball off table is identified, and the ball is put back into play without delay at the goalie rod of the other team.

If the ball cannot be retrieved within a reasonable time then it should be abandoned and a new ball taken from the ball supply.

In general, if the ball strikes a ‘gameplay’ table component then active play continues uninterrupted, and if it strikes a ‘non-gameplay’ table component then the ball is off table and active play stops.

A gameplay component is any table element internal to the table which is necessary for gameplay, including the playfield, playing figures, bumpers, springs, side strips, ramps, side walls, end walls and the length of the rods internal to the playing area. The goal posts and crossbars are considered to be gameplay components even if portions of them are outside the playing area.

Non-gameplay components include tally markers, table fixtures, objects placed on the cabinet, and anything that is external to the frame of the table, for example, the external parts of the rods, the handles, and any serving cup.

The goal assemblies and the top of the cabinet are boundary cases; although they are not gameplay components, the ball remains in play if it strikes one of them and returns to the playing area. However, tally markers are always out of play, even if they are part of a goal assembly.

The ball is off table if it leaves the playing area and:

● strikes a person or any object outside the table (e.g. the floor, ceiling or wall of the room)

● strikes a tally marker

● strikes any fixture attached to the cabinet excluding the goal assembly

● strikes a foreign object resting on the cabinet

● comes to rest on the top of the cabinet

The ball is not off table and active play continues uninterrupted if it returns to the playing area after:

● striking a goal post or crossbar

● striking any part of a goal assembly excluding a tally marker

● bouncing or rolling on the top of the cabinet

● entering a serving hole from the playing area

● going airborne directly above the playing area or the cabinet

Rule: Airborne Catch

A player must not catch or otherwise intentionally interact with a ball that is airborne above the playing area or the cabinet.

Penalty: Penalty Shot; if the Penalty Shot is not scored: 5-rod Possession Award

Rule: Illegal Aerial

A player must not perform a controlled transition that causes the ball to directly overfly an opponent’s rod.

Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Interpretation

1. A defensive block or an immediate defensive reaction is not a controlled transition.

2. Examples of cabinet fixtures include: a light fitting, camera or microphone.

7.4 Interrupts

An interrupt is an exceptional break in play which is not time-limited, one of the following:

● player interrupt

● infraction interrupt

● disruption

A player interrupt is a break initiated by one of the players at the table. An infraction interrupt is initiated by the referee if one is present, or if there is no referee, by one of the players. A disruption is an interruption to play which is not initiated by a player or referee.

If an interrupt occurs during active play then the ball should be held by whichever player has or next gains controlled possession of the ball. Active play is suspended while the interrupt is processed.

When the interrupt has been resolved, or when the referee announces “Play!”, the player with possession must put the ball back into play with a restart.

7.4.1 Player Interrupt

In exceptional situations a player can interrupt active play, for example in order to:

● Declare a rule infraction in the absence of a referee

● Ask permission to clean the ball or playing area

● Request table maintenance

● Relinquish possession of a precarious ball

● Request a referee

● Appeal a referee decision

● Request a medical break

● Tighten a loose handle

It is the responsibility of the player to ensure that a player interrupt is initiated in a timely manner, otherwise they may be in violation of one of the Distraction rules.

Players are permitted to ask the referee or other players a brief question during a break in play or during the restart, for example to query the event format or the number of remaining time-outs. Time control is still in effect.

7.4.2 Disruption

A disruption is an interruption to play which is not initiated by a player or referee, for example a sudden failure of a table component or an external event unrelated to matchplay. Examples of disruptions include:

● A figure breaking

● A lighting failure

● A foreign object entering the playing area

● Consequential interference from a spectator

● A tournament organiser asking play to stop

If a disruption occurs which materially impacts the outcome of a play, then the disrupted play shall not stand, but shall be replayed with a restart from the rod which last had controlled possession.

7.4.3 Infraction Interrupt

An infraction interrupt is a short interrupt that occurs when an infraction is declared, during which the infraction is processed and the appropriate penalty, if any, is determined and applied.

An infraction is processed according to the following steps:

● The infraction is declared and play is suspended

● The ball is held as soon as possible

● The current location of the ball is noted

● The location of the ball when the infraction occurred is noted

● The appropriate penalty, if any, is determined and applied

After the infraction has been processed play continues in accordance with the rules.

When an infraction is declared, active play is suspended and the ball must be stopped and held by whichever player next gains controlled possession of the ball. This is the current location for infraction processing.

If a team commits an infraction during active play then any play by that team resulting from or directly following the infraction shall not count. However, the non-offending team shall also have the additional option to continue play from the current location of the ball, unless the penalty indicated by the rule is only a warning.

Interpretation

1. If a team scores a goal directly following their infraction then the goal shall not count, but if

they score an own goal then the non-offending team has the option to continue from the current location, and so the goal shall count.

7.4.3.1 Without a Referee

In an unrefereed match any player can declare an infraction by calling “Stop!”.

Rule infractions should be declared as soon as possible after they occur. In the case of an infraction during active play the non-offending team will lose the option to declare the infraction once they subsequently perform a controlled transition, in which case they are deemed to have implicitly taken their option to continue play from the current location of the ball.

If active play ends following an infraction, for example if a goal is scored, then the non-offending team should declare any infraction as soon as possible.

Players should resolve any disagreement in an amicable manner, and are permitted to use compromise to do so. If the players cannot resolve the disagreement then a referee should be requested.

7.4.3.2 With a Referee

In a refereed match the players are not permitted to declare infractions. The referee will declare an infraction by calling “Stop!”. Under certain circumstances the referee might delay interrupting play until the outcome of a transition is clear.

A referee’s ruling can be based on information obtained from the players, from spectators, from other referees and from any available video recordings.

7.5 Medical Break Request

A player may request a medical break at any time outside active play, or during active play by performing a player interrupt when the ball is stopped.

The outcome of the request will be determined by the referee, who may also involve the tournament director. In an unrefereed match the request must go directly to the tournament director.

If the request is approved the maximum duration of the medical break will be communicated to the players.

Rule: Medical Break Request Declined

There is a penalty if the request for a medical break is declined. Penalty: Charged Time-out

Rule: Medical Break Expiry

The player must be ready to play after their medical break period has expired. Penalty: Forfeit Match

7.6 Practice

Practice is permitted on any table during the prelude and between games. Practice is not permitted during any other breaks. Performing a transfer or a transition outside of active play is considered to be practice, except when permitted in order to position the ball when putting it into play.

Rule: Illegal Practice

A player must not perform a transfer or a transition during a break, other than between games and where permitted in order to position the ball when putting it into play. Penalty:

● First in match:

○ If the offending team has possession: 5-rod Possession Award ○ If the offending team does not have possession: Warning

● Subsequent in match: Penalty Shot

Interpretation

1. Inadvertently moving the ball is not illegal practice; a referee will use discretion.

9 Referee

Matchplay rules should be respected regardless of the presence of a referee, however if a referee is officiating then infractions cannot be declared by the players, but only by the referee.

The referee’s authority must be respected at all times during the match, and begins when both teams are at the table. A referee’s instructions must be obeyed during a match. Referee judgements must not be challenged, and players are reminded that human error is part of the game.

Rule: Arguing

A player must not argue with an officiating referee.

Penalty: Referee discretion, possible Conduct Violation

9.1 Referee Instructions

Players must be familiar with the following instructions which a referee may issue to indicate the end of a break in play:

Referee call | Reason | Player action
“Time!” | The maximum time allowed for the pause has expired | Restart
“Play!” | Play must now begin | Restart

Players must also be familiar with the following announcements which a referee can make during active play:

Referee call | Reason | Player action
“Stop!” | Referee judgement will be given | The ball must be stopped and held
“Time!” | Possession time infraction | The ball must be stopped and held
“Reset” | Reset infraction | Continue active play
“Reset Warning” | Reset infraction | Continue active play

9.2 Referee Request

A referee can be requested in order to:

● provide a rule interpretation

● resolve a controversy

● continue the match with a referee

In an unrefereed match a player may request a referee at any time outside active play, or during active play after calling “Stop!” when the ball is stopped.

In a refereed match, a player cannot interrupt active play to request a second or replacement referee. A team who requests a second or replacement referee will be charged with a time-out unless the request was made in a time-out which they called.

If two referees are present, the outcome of any request for a replacement will be decided by the head referee, or if unavailable, by the tournament director.

Rule: Illegal Referee Request

A player must not request a second or replacement referee unless they do so during a time-out called by their team.

Penalty:

● If the request was made when the team is allowed to call a time-out: Charged Time-out

● If the request was made at any other time: Penalty Shot

Rule: Replacement Referee Request Declined

In a match where two referees are present, there shall be a penalty if a request for a replacement referee is declined.

Penalty: Penalty Shot

Interpretation

1. In an unrefereed match, a player who does not have possession may request a referee if the

ball is stopped, e.g. if they think that the time limit for rod possession is being exceeded.

2. It is considered a distraction if the defensive team requests a referee at the same time that

the offensive player performs a transition.

9.3 Referee Appeal

A Referee Appeal is an interrupt during which a player appeals to the head referee to make a ruling.

If a player believes a referee at the table has incorrectly enforced or failed to enforce a rule or penalty they may formally appeal to the head referee to get a ruling. The player must inform the referee of their intent to lodge a Referee Appeal at which point the match will be interrupted until a decision is returned.

Any appeal must be lodged before the ball is put back into play. An appeal involving the outcome of a match must be lodged before the winning team has begun its next match.

The head referee shall consult the matchplay rules and at least two other referees (if available) to determine whether or not the referee’s decision should be upheld or overturned.

Rule: Unreasonable Appeal

A player must not challenge a referee’s judgement, or make insubstantial or unreasonable appeals. Penalty: Charged Time-out

11 Passing

A pass is considered to have occurred if the catching rod retains active possession of the ball or performs an immediate controlled transition.

There are some restrictions when passing the ball forward from the 5-rod and the goalie rod. Put simply, a ball must be moving in order to be legally passed. To appreciate the finer details it’s necessary to understand the definition of a restricted ball.

In the context of passing, a ball that is stopped, pinned or adjusted becomes a restricted ball. When passing from the 5-rod to the 3-rod, a restricted ball cannot be passed with either a direct-pass or with an indirect-pass. When passing from the goalie rod to the 5-rod, a restricted ball cannot be passed with a direct-pass, but it can be passed with an indirect-pass. The restriction is cleared by performing a transfer, after which the ball can be legally passed.

There are no restrictions on passes between other rods, or on backward passes between rods.

Passing rod | Catching rod | The pass is illegal if the ball is... | ...and the pass is...
5-rod | 3-rod | Stopped, pinned, adjusted | Direct or indirect
Goalie rod | 5-rod | Stopped, pinned, adjusted | Direct

Rule: Restricted pass

A player must not direct-pass or indirect-pass a restricted ball from the 5-rod to the 3-rod. A player must not direct-pass a restricted ball from a goalie rod to the 5-rod. Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Interpretation

1. It is legal to pass a stationary ball because if the pass is immediate the ball is not stopped.

2. A stopped 5–3 pass is illegal even if it deflects off the opposing 5-rod (indirect).

3. A rocking ball is a stopped ball.

4. A stub pass is legal.

5. Even if the catching rod performs an immediate controlled transition, it's still a pass.

6. There are no restrictions on passing a ball if it goes through more than one of the opposing

team’s rods, for example if it goes off either end wall.

12 Wall Contact

There are restrictions that govern contact between the ball and the wall, and also between the rods and the wall.

If the ball becomes trapped on or near the wall, it must be freed by contact with a figure; it is illegal to attempt to influence the ball by any other means, e.g. by hitting a rod into the wall.

On the 5-rod, the wall contact count cannot exceed two during a single active possession. However, if the ball becomes trapped, multiple consecutive wall contacts may be used until the ball is freed, all of which will count as a single wall contact.

If the ball becomes trapped touching the wall, then the wall contact count is increased by one, but if the ball becomes trapped before it touches the wall, the next wall contact increases the wall contact count by one. In both cases, any subsequent contacts with the wall do not increase the wall contact count, until the ball is freed. Once the ball is freed, each subsequent wall contact will increase the wall contact count.

If two or more wall contacts are used to free a trapped ball then the player must perform a transfer before transitioning the ball.

The wall contact count doesn’t increase if the ball is trapped by the 5-rod directly following a transition.

Wall contacts are counted separately on each side of the table, however, the first wall contact on one side of the table resets the wall contact count on the other side.

Rule: Trapped Ball Influence

A player on the team with active possession of a trapped ball must not influence or attempt to influence the ball by hitting a rod into the wall.

Penalty:

● First in match: Warning

● Subsequent in match: 5-rod Possession Award

Rule: Three Walls

The wall contact count must not exceed two during a single active possession on the 5-rod. Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Rule: Trapped Ball Transition

If a player makes two or more wall contacts to free a trapped ball on the 5-rod, then they must not transition the ball without first performing a transfer. Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

13 Reaching Into the Playing Area

Consent may be required to reach into the playing area, for example, to clean the ball, wipe the playfield, or pick up a dead ball.

Consent is given by the referee, or in an unrefereed match, by the opposing team. Consent requested during active play is treated as a player interrupt; active play is suspended and the interrupt is processed.

Consent is required in order to reach into the playing area to touch the ball except when positioning the ball where allowed during a restart. If it is demonstrated that the ball is dead or precarious, then consent is implicit and the ball may be picked up. In other cases, for example to remove oil or dirt from the ball, consent must be explicitly given.

A player wishing to reach into the playing area during active play must first request consent. Outside active play any player is free to reach into the playing area without consent provided that they do not touch the ball.

Rule: Reaching In During Active Play

During active play a player must not reach into the playing area without consent. Penalty:

● If a moving ball is prevented from entering their team’s goal: Point Award

● If the player touches a precarious ball at their team’s goal: Point Award

● If the ball is stopped and not touched during their team’s possession: 5-rod Possession Award

● All other cases: Penalty Shot

Rule: Ball Handling During Break

During a break a player must not reach into the playing area and touch the ball without consent, unless it is between games.

Penalty:

● If the ball is precarious at their team’s goal: Point Award

● If their team has paused possession: 5-rod Possession Award

● If the other team has paused possession: Penalty Shot

Interpretation

1. Outside active play a player can remove dirt or wipe marks from the playfield without consent.

2. In order to tighten a handle that becomes loose during active play, a player must interrupt

play and gain consent before reaching into the playing area.

3. The referee may decline a request to touch the ball, for example if it is precarious or of

doubtful controllability.

14 Switching Positions

In standard doubles the two players on a team are allowed to switch their playing positions during a time-out, between points, between games and before and after a penalty shot.

During these breaks both teams are free to switch positions until the ready protocol in the subsequent restart has begun. The offensive team is allowed to switch positions until they offer the “Ready?” prompt, and the defensive team is allowed to switch positions until they give the “Ready!” response.

After the “Ready!” response is given and prior to the start of active play neither team is allowed to switch positions unless a time-out is called.

It is an infraction to switch positions during active play.

Players are not permitted to switch positions during the ready protocol in contravention with the above formula, or during a dead ball, a ball off table, or during any interrupt; these are not infractions but any such switch is disallowed and must be reversed. Once active play has begun, a switch which should have been disallowed is not reversed.

Players are not permitted to switch positions during the restart which follows an interrupt, unless they would have been legally allowed to do so at the moment that the interrupt occurred.

If the ready protocol is interrupted at any point then the “Ready?” prompt will be re-issued. Any such interrupt does not restore switching rights to either team; the offensive team cannot switch positions prior to re-issuing the “Ready?” prompt.

Switching positions must be completed in accordance with the time constraint of the break during which it is performed; any delay or disallowed switch may be grounds for a Delay of Game infraction.

Rule: Illegal Switch

The players in a doubles team must not switch positions during active play. Penalty: Distraction

15 Impairing Play

Distraction, reset and jar are actions which impair the other team’s ability to play, and are illegal. They can be classified according to the type of impairment, as follows:

Common name | Impairment of | Description
Distraction | Attention | Pulling the other team’s attention away
Reset | Control | Disrupting a player’s control of the ball
Jarring | Possession | Preventing a player from keeping or gaining possession

15.1 Distraction

A player must not pull the attention of the opposing team away from the game during active play. Impairing attention is a distraction.

A referee may issue a Warning penalty for the first distraction in a match; a subsequent infraction by the same team in the same match will carry a more severe penalty. Distractions are not limited to those identified here; other actions may be grounds for a distraction call, at the discretion of the referee.

The manner in which players take and release control of their rods is potentially distracting. In general players should have their rods under control during active play; they can release handles, e.g. to wipe their hands, to change holds, or to move between rods, but must do so in accordance with the rules. A rod is considered to be under control when a player is holding that rod’s handle using any part of their arm from the elbow down to the fingers. This permits a variety of holds using different parts of the arm, including the fingers, hand, palm, wrist, forearm and elbow.

Rule: Distracting Activity

During active play, and at the discretion of the referee, the following activities may be judged as distractions:

● making sounds, e.g. talking or shouting

● allowing an electronic device on the player’s person to make sound

● excessive movement of the hands between the handles

● excessive movement of a rod that is not part of an offensive or defensive play

● any bodily movement or gesture that is not part of an offensive or defensive play, e.g. tapping the cabinet in apology or approval

● making contact with an opposing team’s rod, i.e. a clash

Penalty: Distraction

Rule: Illegal Rod Control

During active play a player must not:

● control a rod using any part of their body beyond the elbow

● in standard doubles, control a rod not designated for their position

Penalty: Distraction

Rule: Movement Away

When a player has active possession on one rod, another rod on the same team must not hit the wall or be moved excessively.

Penalty: Distraction.

Rule: Reaching Away

A player with active possession must not release both handles and reach down or away from the table.

Penalty: Distraction

Rule: Distracting Transition

In standard doubles a player must not perform a controlled transition when they or their partner are not controlling each rod with each arm.

In standard singles a player must not perform a controlled transition on the 3-rod when their other arm is not controlling another rod.

Penalty: Distraction

Rule: Sudden Play

In standard doubles a player must not perform a controlled transition within one second of either player on the team taking hold of the handle of any rod.

In standard singles a player must not perform a controlled transition on the 3-rod within one second of taking hold of the handle of any rod.

Penalty: Distraction

Momentary release of the handle when changing between holds prior to a transition is not in and of itself a Sudden Play infraction.

Interpretation

1. Moving the catching rod when passing is not a distraction unless that movement is excessive.

2. Spinning a rod may be considered excessive movement.

3. A brief whisper by a player on a team with active possession of a stopped ball is allowed.

15.2 Reset

Impairing a player’s ability to control the ball is illegal. A reset infraction is any shake, bump or shock by a player on the defensive team that impairs the offensive player’s control of the ball.

Upon the first infraction in a game the referee announces "Reset", indicating that the defensive team has committed a reset infraction This means that the non-offending team’s possession clock and 5-rod wall contact count are reset. Active play does not stop when the referee makes a reset call.

After their first “Reset” call in a game, the next infraction by the same team will be a “Reset Warning” call, and any subsequent infraction by the same team during the same point will result in a Penalty Shot. After a Penalty Shot the next infraction by the same team is a “Reset Warning” again.

For each team, the sequence of reset infractions is as follows:

Reset infraction sequence | Referee call | Active play
First in game | “Reset” | Continues
Subsequent in game | “Reset Warning” or “Warning” | Continues
Subsequent in game and second in point | “Stop!” | Stops - Penalty Shot

In the event of reset on the 5-rod, the referee has the discretion to make a 5-rod Possession Award.

A reset occurs when a stopped ball is made to move, although a referee can judge it to have occurred even if the ball is pinned or moving. A rocking ball is not judged as a reset, however a ball that is excessively wobbling in place could be judged as a reset.

Rule: Reset

A player on the defensive team must not cause a shake, bump or shock that impairs the offensive player’s ability to control or to play the ball.

Penalty:

● First in game: Reset Call

● Subsequent in game: Reset Warning

● Subsequent in game and second in point: Penalty Shot

Rule: 5-rod Reset

A player on the defensive team must not cause a Reset which prevents the offensive player from successfully completing a pass from the 5-rod to the 3-rod.

Penalty: Reset call and 5-rod Possession Award

Rule: Self Reset

A player on a team with controlled possession must not cause a shake, bump or shock in an attempt to elicit a Reset call from the referee.

Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Interpretation

1. Active play continues after a Reset call, so the defensive team should remain alert.

15.3 Jarring

Impairing a player’s ability to possess the ball is illegal. A jar is any shake, shock, slam, shift or clash that impairs the other team’s ability to retain or gain possession of the ball.

Jarring infractions can also be called at the discretion of the referee.

Rule: Jar

A player must not cause a shake, shock, slam, shift or clash that impairs the other team’s ability to retain or gain controlled possession of the ball. Penalty:

● First and second in match: Restart or 5-rod Possession Award

● Subsequent in match: Penalty Shot

Interpretation

1. A simultaneous slam and transition from the same rod may be grounds for a jarring infraction.

2. Any slamming of the rod during active play may be judged a jar.

3. A shake, bump or shock behind the rod of possession by the defending team is treated as a jar rather than a reset (i.e. when one forward impairs the possession of the other forward).

15.4 Player Conduct

Players must behave ethically and respectfully during a match. The referee has the discretion to determine the penalty or the escalation process in the case of a Conduct Violation.

Rule: Cheating

A player must not cheat or attempt to cheat.

Penalty: Conduct Violation

Rule: Cursing

A player must not curse.

Penalty: Referee discretion, possible Penalty Shot or Conduct Violation

Rule: Derogatory Comment

A player must not make derogatory or inappropriate comments about other players or officials, either directly or indirectly.

Penalty: Referee discretion; possible Penalty Shot

Rule: Illegal Coaching

A player must not receive assistance from a spectator at any point in a match, except during time-outs or between games.

Penalty: Conduct Violation

Rule: Device Usage

A player must not use headphones, earbuds, a mobile phone or any other electronic device during a match, apart from during time-outs or between games. Penalty (first in match): Warning

Penalty (subsequent in match): Penalty Shot

Rule: Table Abuse

A player must not slam any rod or forcefully shake or shift the table, even outside active play. Penalty: Conduct Violation

Rule: Aggression

A player must not threaten or behave aggressively towards any other person. Penalty: Conduct Violation

Rule: Format Deviation

Teams must not play a different format than the one specified for the event. Penalty: Conduct Violation

15.5 Spectator Conduct

Spectators are subject to Conduct Violations at referee discretion. Spectators must not coach or distract players during active play.

Rule: Spectator Coaching

A spectator must not influence or attempt to influence a match by transmitting information to a player, except during time-outs or between games.

Penalty: Conduct Violation

Rule: Spectator Distraction

A spectator must not influence a match by distracting the players or the referee. Penalty: Conduct Violation, possible expulsion

16 Changes to the Table

16.1 Routine Maintenance

Players are allowed to briefly wipe the playfield without permission outside active play, provided that no substance is used to do so.

Players may lubricate their own team’s rods during time-outs and between games. Pipette or sponge applicators must be used when applying lubricant directly to the rods. Lubricant must not be sprayed directly onto the rods, but can be applied indirectly. The Tournament Director may require the use of specific lubricant products, and may mandate specific requirements and restrictions for their use.

A player can use a substance to improve handle grip provided that they ensure that it does not get into the playing area or onto the rods or the ball.

Where permitted by the tournament director, players are allowed to replace their handles with other approved handles. This can be done during any pause provided that it is done within the time limits.

16.2 Table Maintenance

If there is a sudden alteration to the table or to table fixture such as the table lighting, or a foreign object enters the playing area, then the appropriate table maintenance should be performed.

If the table requires cleaning, approved products may be used in accordance with table manufacturer and event promoter specifications and restrictions.

If the problem cannot be resolved by the players, a table maintenance request should be made at the tournament desk.

The table may be levelled during the prelude. Once active play has started in the match a player may only request to level the table during a pause. If both teams agree to level the table then this can be done either by the players or by a table maintenance request made at the tournament desk.

After the problem is resolved, the ball shall be put back into play by the player with possession. However, if the sudden alteration was a disruption which materially impacted the outcome of a play, then the disrupted play shall not stand, but shall be replayed with a restart from the rod which last had controlled possession.

Rule: Levelling Request

If the other team disagrees with a player’s request to level the table, then the requesting team shall call table maintenance and will be charged with a time-out. Penalty: Charged Time-out

Interpretation

1. Sudden alterations include: a broken playing figure, pin, screw, spring or bumper, a bent rod,

a failure of table lighting

16.3 Illegal Modification

A player must not modify the playing characteristics of the table or the balls.

Rule: Table Modification

A player must not make any modification to the playing characteristics of the table or the ball. Penalty: Referee discretion, possible Penalty Shot or Exclusion

Rule: Rod Limiting

A player must not use any device or object that limits the movement of a rod. Penalty: Referee discretion, possible Penalty Shot

Rule: Contamination

A player must not allow the playfield or the ball to become contaminated by any substance. Penalty:

● First in match: Warning

● Subsequent in match: Penalty Shot

Rule: Illegal Cleaning

A player must not use any substance, including saliva or sweat, to wipe marks off the playfield or the ball. Penalty:

● First in match: Warning

● Subsequent in match: Penalty Shot

Rule: Substance on Handle

When changing table sides between games, a player must not leave any substance on the handles. Penalty:

● First in match: Warning, player is required to remove the substance within the time limits

● Subsequent in match: Prohibition from using the substance

Interpretation

1. Examples of table modification include: filing a playing figure, sandpapering the playfield, and

directly applying a foreign substance to the playfield, the playing figure or the ball.

2. Examples of contaminants include: lubricant and substances used to improve handle grip.

17 Penalty Shot

A referee can award a Penalty Shot to the non-offending team for a serious violation of the rules; these cases are explicitly identified in the relevant rules. The referee also has the discretion to award a Penalty Shot for flagrant or intentional violation of the rules.

The Penalty Shot is a single 3-rod possession awarded to the non-offending team in an attempt to score a goal against one defensive player from the offending team.

The player on the non-offending team who takes the Penalty Shot is here called the penalty taker, and the player on the offending team who defends the shot is here called the defender.

In a standard doubles match one player from each team must leave the table before the Penalty Shot is taken. However, the players in each team may first switch positions before the two players who are not involved in the Penalty Shot leave the table.

The ball is put into play with a 3-rod restart by the penalty taker and the transition is performed. During the Penalty Shot all Standard Matchplay Rules are in force.

If the penalty taker’s transition results in a legally scored goal, then the Penalty Shot is complete and the point is marked by the penalty taker.

The Penalty Shot is also complete in the event of any of the following outcomes:

● A rule infraction with a penalty other than a Warning, committed by the penalty taker

● The penalty taker’s transition goes backwards

● After the penalty taker’s transition

○ the ball becomes reachable by the defender’s 2-rod and then subsequently becomes

unreachable forward of the defender’s 2-rod

○ the ball stops moving

○ the ball goes off table

When the Penalty Shot is complete, the referee may issue a Warning that further infractions by the offending team will result in forfeiture of the game or the match.

After the Penalty Shot is complete the players return to the table; in standard doubles either team may again Switch Positions.

After the players return to the table play continues as follows:

● If the point was scored then the offending team restarts with a kick-off

● If the point was not scored then restart from the location of the infraction or as specified in

accordance with the rules

Rule: Penalty Shot Limit

A team must not be charged with three Penalty Shots in one game. Penalty: Forfeit Game

18 Penalties

This section identifies the penalties for rule infractions.

Penalty: Continue

In the event of a rule infraction during active play for which the penalty given is not a Warning, in addition to the penalty specified below the non-offending team shall also have the option to continue from the current location of the ball.

Penalty: Warning

A warning indicates that a subsequent infraction of a similar nature will carry a more severe penalty.

Penalty: Goalie rod Possession Award

Possession of the ball is awarded to the non-offending team for a restart on any goalie rod figure.

Penalty: 5-rod Possession Award

Possession of the ball is awarded to the non-offending team for a restart at the central 5-rod figure.

Penalty: Restart or 5-rod Possession Award

The non-offending team can choose to restart from the location where the infraction occurred or take a 5-rod Possession Award.

Penalty: Reset Call

The referee announces "Reset!" and the possession clock and wall contact count are reset. The next reset infraction will result in a Reset Warning penalty.

Penalty: Reset Warning

The referee announces "Reset Warning!" and the possession clock and wall contact count are reset.

Penalty: Distraction (first in match)

● If deemed benign by the referee: Warning

● If a goal was scored by the offending team: Goal disallowed and 5-rod Possession Award

● All other cases: Restart or 5-rod Possession Award

Penalty: Distraction (subsequent in match) Referee discretion: Restart or 5-rod Possession Award, or possible Penalty Shot.

Penalty: Charged Time-out

A team that is charged with a time-out loses one of their remaining time-outs in the game. The team is entitled to take the full period of the time-out only if they could have legally called a time-out at that point in the match.

Penalty: Point Award

The non-offending team is awarded a point. The offending team then has the kick-off.

Penalty: Forfeit Game

The team forfeit the game.

Penalty: Forfeit Match

The team forfeit the match.

Penalty: Conduct Violation

At the discretion of the referee, and in accordance with the severity of the infraction, any penalty from a warning to the forfeiture of a game or the match. Also, by escalation to the head referee and/or tournament director, expulsion from the tournament venue or a fine.

Penalty: Penalty Shot

See Penalty Shot section for details.